<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Syed Zayyan Masud - thoughts</title>
	<subtitle>A personal portfolio&#x2F;blog website of Syed Zayyan Masud</subtitle>
	<link href="https://syedzayyan.com/tags/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://syedzayyan.com"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-10-29T23:00:01+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://syedzayyan.com/tags/thoughts/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>From Everything to Zola</title>
		<published>2022-10-29T23:00:01+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-10-29T23:00:01+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://syedzayyan.com/posts/from-everything-to-zola/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://syedzayyan.com/posts/from-everything-to-zola/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of rebuilding this blog often. Usually happens when I am trying to learn a new language or thing. This is like the comfort project that I can come back to. I used to think that this was a bad habit and just a thing I do when I am anxious. Surprisingly it&#x27;s not. It&#x27;s actually quite the opposite. David Thomas (the author of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pragprog.com&#x2F;titles&#x2F;tpp20&#x2F;the-pragmatic-programmer-20th-anniversary-edition&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Pragmatic Programmer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) mentioned in his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pragdave.me&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2020&#x2F;05&#x2F;05&#x2F;advice-on-learning-a-language.html&quot;&gt;blog&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that it&#x27;s easier to learn a language that way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first iteration was hosted on Heroku, and built using Django-Rest. I built the front end using React and used MUI. It was something of a mess but it was easy to build in a few days. Everything went fine. I got to pick up React and its Hooks and work with a Rest API. It was during the first wave of COVID.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quickly I learnt that React when it&#x27;s not an SPA has problems with SEO. Since Google does not sweep JavaScript and only looks at the HTML it missed all the meta tags and title tags when using something like Helmet. I moved to NextJS. NextJS did not require a backend as such. I made all cool animations using framer motion. I added comments, users via NextAuth, Google OAuth and used AWS’s Amazon DocumentDB. I forget the name. I maintained this facade for a while but I didn&#x27;t like the website as such as it still used MUI and didn&#x27;t have my kind of style. It worked though so I kept it on and added sad cringe poetry. Yes I deleted the whole project from GitHub. But I learnt NextJS and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;drreiter.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;landed a freelancing gig&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. My only one till date.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved to Hugo because I was learning GoLang at the time and the themes were simple enough and just what I wanted. I know Hugo doesn&#x27;t really need GoLang under the hood but emotions are illogical. I did write more though. Like good articles. I didn&#x27;t know GitHub Actions, so I manually built the site deployed to GitHub Pages. This went on until I moved back to NextJS with a markdown converter and all on GitHub. I hosted the app on Vercel so all was taken care of.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then enter now. Moving between countries, universities, job rejections later I have a lot of free time. I wanted to learn Typescript. Remember Pragmatic Programmer? Yeah it&#x27;s my inspiration now for all things programming. I converted my &lt;a href=&quot;wellplatelayout.xyz&#x2F;&quot;&gt;well plate app&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to react typescript from Svelte. Because I found this website seemed to daunting to rebuild again that too from NextJS.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing that, I wanted to rebuild my site because I don&#x27;t like Vercel as well. NextJS seems to locked to a Vendor. Enter Zola. Its simple. The lack of likeable themes meant I needed to learn the template which is actually pretty simple. Its on Zola now. I intend to publish a theme that I frankensteined from various themes for my site. Hopefully, everything goes alright contributing to open source for the first time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>A day in London without the tube</title>
		<published>2022-03-04T18:06:01+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-03-04T18:06:01+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://syedzayyan.com/posts/a-day-in-london-without-the-tube/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://syedzayyan.com/posts/a-day-in-london-without-the-tube/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our perception of time is strongly linked to our memories. The more I experience things, the more I feel I have grown as a person and spent more time on this planet. The London tube sort of takes away that experience of traveling on foot or on a bus and seeing the city. I feel this way partly because I use the same line everyday, and probably see the same people. However, no one really looks at each other on the tube, and it&#x27;s usually me reading a book or listening to heavy metal to drown out the harsh sound of the central line, gazing aimlessly outside the windows as I bob my head to the blast beats. On a bus, I have a window into life on the road and very different sorts of people on the bus itself. On foot it is even more interesting, seeing other people wheeze through into the hustle-bustle.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I live in a small town called Ashford. I will skip the boring details, but I have to travel to London weekly, to attend in-person lectures for my bachelors in Pharmacology at QMUL. I could have skipped lectures on the 3rd of March 2022. I did not partly because I am a massive idiot  and partly because I thought I could just use the bus with ease. I forgot buses would have to handle the extra pressure and take more time. There was something else I noticed throughout the strike. London without a tube is just like a person without a personality. The tube almost defines London for me now. Yes you do have your parks, old timely buildings, a funny blue bridge - but you get them in other cities as well. Well maybe not the blue bridge but the tube just is like the icing on the cake. The nebulousness of the network, hot airtight carriages, the busy stations and the noise. It&#x27;s like a whole city underneath the main city. I saw a stream of people as I sat on the bus today. It almost felt as if half of these people live in the tube.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take the bus regularly in Ashford. One thing is common between buses in a town and the city. They are always late and always on time when you are late. I feel this is an unwritten rule. Today was a bad day, but I traveled on buses in London before the lockdown. It has the same exact timing phenomenon. People on the bus seem to be a lot more varied in London. It&#x27;s always different kinds of characters that get on the buses. The drivers are bit more jerky, but I blame the city&#x27;s insufferable traffic for that. In the town, the drivers are slower and sober. It&#x27;s always the same kind of people on the bus. Usually its: a couple of elderly ladies and gents; a teenage boy almost as if diving into his phone; a teenage girl clearly in their rebel phase with gothic kind of makeup; a handful of children making irritable noises incessantly as their guardians bang their heads regretting not using a condom and a few doctors here and there (the bus line I use has a hospital at one end).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tube however does not give a chance to glance at people. Partly because I am scared to make eye contact, and partly because everyone is looking down on their phones or reading a book. But there&#x27;s always similar kinds of people. The bookish ones deep and lost in their texts (this is me), the bobbing their head ones to trap beats, the staring blankly at the window ones, the creep undressing their victim with sheer power of their eyes, the couple making out near the door (it specially hurts during Valentine week) and sometimes an elderly couple. It&#x27;s always old people coupled on tubes. Always. Always restores my faith in love.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all the new experiences (I did not want to) I&#x27;d rather have a mundane journey, because you could only observe so much and experience the difference. The routes will be same, and sooner or later the person on the buses will be same. There will be some other stereotype I will find, and my window into the world will soon be replaced by another book. London traffic will kill me before any of that happens. It&#x27;s so much faster on the tube! But I do feel, now I would take a bus on and off and hopefully not because of a strike. Sometimes, I will need my window into the world in my journey and the buses dawned in red will be ready just late by half an hour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>The world ends?</title>
		<published>2022-02-25T23:00:01+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-02-25T23:00:01+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://syedzayyan.com/posts/the-world-ends/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://syedzayyan.com/posts/the-world-ends/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I sit across my laptop screen, panicking and being anxious about the point of existence, there are people with their worlds toppling over. To be fair I am anxious as a knock-on effect. Now if we have learned anything from the 1940s, you don&#x27;t even need balls to deharmonise the world. One ball is just enough. But we are human beings and we do not learn from our blunders. We make them again and again. 1940s was a curious case of identity politics at play and how it takes one psychopath, with a broken sense of identity. We like to classify it into a religion box, perhaps a racial discrimination box but that&#x27;s what it was - a person with a distorted sense of identity. Is it true for Russia, with a new wave Hitler helmed as the president?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Putin&#x27;s Russia can be easily dismissed as the old school geopolitics fightings its end, but that is boring (although good enough for a drawing room discussion), it is complicated and marred by the situation that Russia has brought onto itself by attacking Ukraine. What Putin, brought to Russian politics was ideology. What a heavy word to throw in, but essentially it means a collection of ideas that forms the basis of an economic policy. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now why is ideology necessary? Human beings have an apparent need to be identified (isothymia) as being equal to others. The line of feeling this &amp;quot;equalness&amp;quot; (for the lack of a better word) can be anything really. On a basic level, being considered a human and on a superficial level it could be like being associated with a culture. And, to form a nation an association is needed that unites people. Why else would you go to think of best interests of a collection of people even to an extent that you go to war with other nations to act in the best interest (jingoism)?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to Russia. What is their ideology? Post USSR Russia did not really have an ideology, considering communism that took the crown for an ideology failed miserably. The rise of Putin and his foreign policy indicates that the Russian people subconsciously needed just a common enemy. A common enemy is a very good factor that could constitute a nation. The West has played the role of an enemy with ease by pushing NATO eastwards and vindicating Russia as a villain. The more Russia feels threatened by such actions, as in not accounting its collective identity and its intentions, the more they tend to fight back (aggresive foreign policies). It&#x27;s as if the West has stopped accounting Russia as an equal by its vindictive actions. And this feeling of injustice is not a subconscious and hidden fact, rather something that has been translated and transmitted by many media outlets, in the West.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putin became the poster boy of an ideology wrapped in nostalgia. Besides being an ex-USSR guy, he wants everyone under that banner again however banal and barmy that maybe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that alone does not account for Russia&#x27;s and specifically Putin&#x27;s actions. Putin does have megalothymic (treating onself as more than others) tendencies. Now if you know about Psychopaths and the Bob Hare checklist, that is one of the items, grandiose sense of self. And Bob Hare has himself questioned if there are couple of psychopaths that topple world order with their madness and that is an interesting fact to consider. And a quick Google search confirms you that (, but seriously they are legitimate pieces on this). So is it really that something hurt a madman&#x27;s sense of identity? I think it is. However crazy that idea is (I know ironic!) I think there is some truth to this. Just like the UBLs, Hitlers and the Mussolinis of the world I feel it is a madman hurt, and we are doing absolutely nothing to address that problem. To be fair there&#x27;s nothing we can really do. It&#x27;s just the rule of the world now to engage in wars each lifetime until we kill off each other.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References: &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity: Contemporary Identity Politics and the Struggle for Recognition by Francis Fukuyama&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Psychopath Test by Jon Ronson&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.jstor.org&#x2F;stable&#x2F;26414074&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
